Normalization
Normalization is a systematic approach of decomposing tables to eliminate data redundancy and undesirable
characteristics like Insertion, Update and Deletion anomalies.
▪ These would include two properties
o Lossless join property - which guarantees that the generation of spurious tuples will not occur.
o Dependency preservation property - This ensures that each functional dependency is represented in
some individual relation resulting after decomposition.
▪ Prime attribute - An attribute of relation schema R is called a prime attribute of R if it is a member
of some candidate key of R.
▪ Non-prime attribute - An attribute is called nonprime if it is not a prime attribute—that is, if it is
not a member of any candidate key.